export const tokiPonaList = [
    {
        front: "a",
        back: ["uh", "Ahh!", "!", "ha!"],
    },
    {
        front: "kin",
        back: ["yes", "indeed", "also"]
    },
    {
        front: "ala",
        back: ["no", "not", "none", "un-"]
    },
    {
        front: "alasa",
        back: ["hunt", "find", "search", "pursue"]
    },
    {
        front: "ale or ali",
        back: ["everything", "life", "100%"]
    },
    {
        front: "anpa",
        back: ["down", "below", "lessen"]
    },
    {
        front: "ante",
        back: ["different", "changed", "other"]
    },
    {
        front: "anu",
        back: ["or", "either", "choice", "decision"]
    },
    {
        front: "awen",
        back: ["stay", "wait", "endure", "maintain"]
    },
    {
        front: "e",
        back: ["to", "for", "towards", "by"]
    },
    {
        front: "en",
        back: ["and", "with", "plus", "join"]
    },
    {
        front: "esun",
        back: ["market", "trade", "business"]
    },
    {
        front: "ijo",
        back: ["thing", "fact", "occurrence"]
    },
    {
        front: "ike",
        back: ["bad", "complex", "chaotic"]
    },
    {
        front: "ilo",
        back: ["tool", "device", "instrument"]
    },
    {
        front: "insa",
        back: ["inside", "inner", "interior", "stomach"]
    },
    {
        front: "jaki",
        back: ["dirty", "gross", "contaminated", "trash"]
    },
    {
        front: "jan",
        back: ["person", "human", "being", "someone"]
    },
    {
        front: "jelo",
        back: ["yellow", "light green"]
    },
    {
        front: "jo",
        back: ["have", "contain", "hold", "own"]
    },
    {
        front: "kala",
        back: ["fish", "seafood", "creature", "meat"]
    },
    {
        front: "kalama",
        back: ["sound", "noise", "voice", "music"]
    },
    {
        front: "kama",
        back: ["come", "arrive", "come", "arrive"]
    },
    {
        front: "kasi",
        back: ["plant", "tree", "leaf", "flower"]
    },
    {
        front: "ken",
        back: ["can", "able", "may", "allow"]
    },
    {
        front: "kepeken",
        back: ["use", "with", "by means of"]
    },
    {
        front: "kili",
        back: ["fruit", "vegetable", "mushroom", "plant"]
    },
    {
        front: "kin",
        back: ["also", "too", "even", "still"]
    },
    {
        front: "kiwen",
        back: ["hard", "solid", "rock", "metal"]
    },
    {
        front: "ko",
        back: ["goo", "paste", "powder"]
    },
    {
        front: "kon",
        back: ["wind", "smell", "soul", "weather"]
    },
    {
        front: "kule",
        back: ["color", "paint", "color", "paint"]
    },
    {
        front: "kulupu",
        back: ["group", "community"]
    },
    {
        front: "kute",
        back: ["listen", "hear", "listen"]
    },
    {
        front: "la",
        back: ["at", "in", "during", "on"]
    },
    {
        front: "lape",
        back: ["sleep", "rest", "sleep", "rest"]
    },
    {
        front: "laso",
        back: ["blue", "green"]
    },
    {
        front: "lawa",
        back: ["head", "brain", "main", "lead"]
    },
    {
        front: "len",
        back: ["clothing", "cloth"]
    },
    {
        front: "lete",
        back: ["cold", "freeze", "winter", "uncooked"]
    },
    {
        front: "li",
        back: ["is", "are", "am", "does", "do"]
    },
    {
        front: "lili",
        back: ["small", "short", "few", "young"]
    },
    {
        front: "linja",
        back: ["long", "string", "hair", "road"]
    },
    {
        front: "lipu",
        back: ["book", "record", "document", "page"]
    },
    {
        front: "loje",
        back: ["red", "orange"]
    },
    {
        front: "lon",
        back: ["be", "exist", "real", "located at"]
    },
    {
        front: "luka",
        back: ["hand", "arm", "five"]
    },
    {
        front: "lukin",
        back: ["see", "watch", "read", "observe"]
    },
    {
        front: "lupa",
        back: ["door", "hole", "window", "entrance"]
    },
    {
        front: "ma",
        back: ["earth", "terrain", "ground", "floor"]
    },
    {
        front: "mama",
        back: ["parent", "ancestor", "creator"]
    },
    {
        front: "mani",
        back: ["money", "savings", "wealth", "cattle"]
    },
    {
        front: "meli",
        back: ["woman", "female", "wife"]
    },
    {
        front: "mi",
        back: ["I", "we", "my", "our"]
    },
    {
        front: "mije",
        back: ["male", "man", "husband"]
    },
    {
        front: "moku",
        back: ["food", "eat", "drink", "consume"]
    },
    {
        front: "moli",
        back: ["death", "die", "kill", "fatal"]
    },
    {
        front: "monsi",
        back: ["back", "behind", "butt", "rear"]
    },
    {
        front: "mu",
        back: ["bark", "belch", "cough", "yawn"]
    },
    {
        front: "mun",
        back: ["moon", "star", "night sky object"]
    },
    {
        front: "musi",
        back: ["fun", "play", "game", "joke"]
    },
    {
        front: "mute",
        back: ["many", "several", "very", "quantity"]
    },
    {
        front: "namako",
        back: ["extra", "supplement", "improvement"]
    },
    {
        front: "nanpa",
        back: ["number", "amount", "count", "measure"]
    },
    {
        front: "nasa",
        back: ["silly", "stupid", "weird", "unusual"]
    },
    {
        front: "nasin",
        back: ["custom", "manner","doctrine", "method"]
    },
    {
        front: "nena",
        back: ["bump", "hill", "nose", "protuberance"]
    },
    {
        front: "ni",
        back: ["this", "that", "these", "those"]
    },
    {
        front: "nimi",
        back: ["word", "name"]
    },
    {
        front: "noka",
        back: ["leg", "foot"]
    },
    {
        front: "o",
        back: ["hey", "oi", "yo", "hello"]
    },
    {
        front: "oko",
        back: ["eye", "see", "look"]
    },
    {
        front: "olin",
        back: ["love", "like", "friendship"]
    },
    {
        front: "ona",
        back: ["he", "she", "it", "they"]
    },
    {
        front: "open",
        back: ["open", "start", "begin"]
    },
    {
        front: "pakala",
        back: ["botched", "broken", "damaged"]
    },
    {
        front: "pali",
        back: ["work", "do", "make", "build"]
    },
    {
        front: "palisa",
        back: ["stick", "rod", "branch"]
    },
    {
        front: "pan",
        back: ["grain", "cereal", "bread", "pasta"]
    },
    {
        front: "pana",
        back: ["give", "send", "release", "put"]
    },
    {
        front: "pi",
        back: ["of", "belonging to", "for", "about"]
    },
    {
        front: "pilin",
        back: ["feel", "emotion", "heart"]
    },
    {
        front: "pimeja",
        back: ["black", "dark"]
    },
    {
        front: "pini",
        back: ["end", "stop", "past", "done", ]
    },
    {
        front: "pipi",
        back: ["bug", "insect", "ant", "spider"]
    },
    {
        front: "poka",
        back: ["side", "near", "beside", "with"]
    },
    {
        front: "poki",
        back: ["box", "bowl", "bag", "pocket"]
    },
    {
        front: "pona",
        back: ["good", "simple", "nice", "right"]
    },
    {
        front: "pu",
        back: ["book", "manual", "doctrine"]
    },
    {
        front: "sama",
        back: ["same", "similar", "equal", "alike"]
    },
    {
        front: "seli",
        back: ["warm", "hot", "fire", "cook"]
    },
    {
        front: "selo",
        back: ["outside", "surface", "skin", "shell"]
    },
    {
        front: "seme",
        back: ["where", "who", "why", "how", "when"]
    },
    {
        front: "sewi",
        back: ["high", "above", "superior", "divine"]
    },
    {
        front: "sijelo",
        back: ["body", "physical state", "health"]
    },
    {
        front: "sike",
        back: ["circle", "ball", "year", "cycle"]
    },
    {
        front: "sin",
        back: ["new", "fresh", "another", "more"]
    },
    {
        front: "sina",
        back: ["you", "your"]
    },
    {
        front: "sinpin",
        back: ["front", "foremost", "face", "wall"]
    },
    {
        front: "sitelen",
        back: ["picture", "write", "draw", "paint"]
    },
    {
        front: "sona",
        back: ["knowledge", "wisdom", "understand", "learn"]
    },
    {
        front: "soweli",
        back: ["animal", "beast", "land mammal"]
    },
    {
        front: "suli",
        back: ["big", "long", "adult", "important"]
    },
    {
        front: "suno",
        back: ["sun", "light", "day", "bright"]
    },
    {
        front: "supa",
        back: ["horizontal surface", "table"]
    },
    {
        front: "suwi",
        back: ["sweet", "fragrent", "cute", "innocent"]
    },
    {
        front: "tan",
        back: ["by", "from", "because of"]
    },
    {
        front: "taso",
        back: ["but", "only", "however"]
    },
    {
        front: "tawa",
        back: ["moving", "going to", "toward", "moving"]
    },
    {
        front: "telo",
        back: ["water", "liquid", "wet"]
    },
    {
        front: "tenpo",
        back: ["time", "moment", "duration", "situation"]
    },
    {
        front: "toki",
        back: ["language", "talk", "speak", "communicate"]
    },
    {
        front: "tomo",
        back: ["house", "home", "building", "room"]
    },
    {
        front: "tu",
        back: ["two", "pair", "double", "divide"]
    },
    {
        front: "unpa",
        back: ["to have sex"]
    },
    {
        front: "uta",
        back: ["mouth", "lips", "oral"]
    },
    {
        front: "utala",
        back: ["battle", "challenge", "oppose"]
    },
    {
        front: "walo",
        back: ["white", "pale"]
    },
    {
        front: "wan",
        back: ["one", "unify", "unique", "whole"]
    },
    {
        front: "waso",
        back: ["bird", "winged animal"]
    },
    {
        front: "wawa",
        back: ["strong", "confident", "sure", "powerful"]
    },
    {
        front: "weka",
        back: ["away", "absent", "ignored"]
    },
    {
        front: "wile",
        back: ["want", "need", "must", "should"]
    }

];